［ワキツレ］そもそもこれは
([WAKIZURE] To begin with,)
一條の院に仕へ奉る。
(I am in the service of the Emperor Ichijo.)
橘の道成とは我が事なり。
(I am known as Tachibana no Michinari.)
さても帝今夜奇特の御霊夢ましまして。
(It so happens that his Lordship)
三条の小鍛冶宗近に。
(has this night had a portentous dream oracle.)
御剣を打たせらるべきとの
(The Sanjo swordsmith Munechika)
宣旨只今成り下りて候程に。
(must be ordered to forge a blade.)
この由を宗近に申し付ばやと
(I am on my way now to tell Munechika)
存候う。
(of this matter.)
［ワキツレ］いかに此の内に宗近のわたり候か。
([WAKIZURE] Is Munechika at home ?)
［ワキ］誰にてわたり候ふぞ。
([WAKI] Who is it that has come here ?)
［ワキツレ］是は宣旨にて候。
([WAKIZURE] I am a messenger from the Emperor.)
我が君今夜不思議の霊夢ましまして。
(His Majesty has this night had a marvelous oracle in a dream.)
御剣を打たせられるべしとの御事なり。
(According to the oracle, you must forge a fine sword for him.)
とうとう仕り候へ。
(Please comply with this order at once.)
［ワキ］宣旨畏つて承り候 さりながら
([WAKI] While I certainly must agree to execute this imperial order,)
折節相鎚打つべきものの無く候をば
(as I do not have anyone to assist me,)
何とつかまつり候べき。
(I do not know how I will be able to carry it out.)
［ワキツレ］不思議の事を申すものかな。
([WAKIZURE] What you say sir, seems most strange.)
その名を得たる何時なるが
(To hear that someone of your reputation)
相鎚打つべきものの無きとは。
(does not have an appropriate assistant,)
心得難き言い事かな。
(is the most unfortunate news.)
［ワキ］これは仰せにて候へども
([WAKI] Even though I am commanded to do so,)
かようの一大事の物を仕るには
(without an assistant whose skills are equal to my own,)
我に劣らぬ程の物の相鎚仕りてこそ。
(it will not be possible to fulfill this order)
御剣をも打ち申すべけれ
(to forge an imperial blade.)
とにかくに御返事を申しかね。
(This is the answer I must give,)
赤面さしたるばかりなり。
(though I am overcome with embarassment.)
［ワキツレ］申すところはさることなれども。
([WAKIZURE] Even though it may be as you say,)
帝も不思議の霊夢ましませば。
(yet as this is the Emperor's wonderful dream oracle,)
いかなることか候べき
(it surely must be relied upon)
頼もしく思ひ申しつつ
(and you must quickly say)
はやはや領掌申すべしと
(you will accept the order.)
重ねて宣旨ありければ。
(Let me repeat the imperial command!)
［ワキ］此上はとにもかくにも宗近が
([WAKI] At this point, in any case, Munechika)
［地謡］とにもかくにも宗近が
([JIUTAI] In any case, Munechika)
進退ここに谷まりて
(must here decide his course of action.)
御剣の刃の乱るゝ心なりけり。
(Like the ripples beaten along a well-forged blade, his heart wavers.)
さりながら御政道 直なる今の御代なれば。
(Yet, as the reign in the present age is righteous,)
若しも奇特のありやせん。
(a miracle may well be afforded me.)
それのみ頼む心かな。
(I must place my trust only in this.)
［ワキツレ］宣旨に任せとうとう御剣を仕り候へ。
([WAKIZURE] Hurry and make the sword.)
［ワキ］畏って候。
([WAKI] Yes, sir.)
［ワキ］これは一大事を仰せ出されて候ふものかな。
([WAKI] This is a great task you have come to give me.)
かやうの御事は神力を頼むならは別義なく候。
(Such a command can be carried out if I ask for divine help.)
某が氏の神は稲荷の明神にて候程に。
(As my family deity is Inari no Myojin,)
これより直に稲荷に参り。
(I will go at once to Inari,)
この事祈誓申さばやと存じ候。
(and pray concerning this matter.)
［シテ］なう／＼あれなるは三条の小鍛冶宗近にて御入り候ふか。
([SHITE] Ho there! Is that the Swordsmith of Sanjō, Munechika ?)
［ワキ］不思議やななべてならざる御事の。
([WAKI] How mysterious! Here is someone who is certainly not an ordinary person.)
道もなき方より来たり給ひ
(There is no path from the direction from which he has appeared,)
我が名をさして宣ふは。
(and now he has called me by name.)
いかなる人にてましますぞ。
(What manner of man are you ?)
［シテ］雲の上なる君よりも
([SHITE] You have been ordered)
剣を打ちて参らせよと。
(by his Imperial Majesty)
汝に仰せありしよなう。
(to forge a sword!)
［ワキ］さればこそ
([WAKI] As I thought, you are not what you seem to be,)
それにつけてもなほ／＼奇特の御事なれ。
(and events must be of great importance indeed.)
剣の勅も只今なるを。
(I have just received the order to make a blade!)
早くも知ろしめさるる事
(How could it be that anyone could know so soon ?)
返す／＼も不審なり。
(No matter how I consider it, the matter is most strange.)
［シテ］げにげにそれはさる事なれども
([SHITE] In truth, it is as you say. It is said: To know a thing one's self,)
我のみ知れば諸人までも。
(is to find it known to all.)
［ワキ］天に声あり。
([WAKI] A voice in heaven,)
［シテ］地に響く。
([SHITE] echoes on the earth!)
［地謡］壁に耳。
([JIUTAI] Wall have ears:)
岩の物いふ世の中に
(In the world where rocks may speak,)
岩の物いふ世の中に。
隠はあらじ殊になほ。
(and nothing is hidden,)
雲の上人の御剣の。
(nothing shall dim the radiance)
光は何か闇からん。
(of the Emperor's sword.)
唯頼めこの君の。
(Only have faith)
恵によらば御剣も
(that through his Majesty's grace and the sword)
などか心に適はざる。
(will be realized as you wish.)
などかは適はざるべき。
(It must be realized.)
それ漢王三尺の剣
([JIUTAI] Once with such a blade, the Emperor's Three Foot Sword,)
居ながら秦の乱を治め。
(subdued the rebellion of the Ts'in by its reputation alone.)
又煬帝がけいの剣。
(Again, the Yang Emperor, with his sword Kei)
周室の光を奪へり。
(outshone the brillance of the House of Chou.)
［シテ］その後玄宗皇帝の鍾馗大臣も
([SHITE] In later years, the Emperor Huan Tsung's Minister Chung K'ei too,)
［地謡］剣の徳に魂魄は
([JIUTAI] joined his spirit after death with the virtue of his sword,)
君辺に仕へ奉り。
(and thus served at his Lord's side.)
魍魎鬼神に至るまで。
(Even evil spirits and demons)
剣の刃の光。に恐れて
(were in fear of that sword's glow,)
其寇をなす事を得ず。
(and the destruction they sought was not achieved.)
漢家本朝に於て剣の威徳
([SHITE] Indeed, the virtue of the swords in China and Japan)
申すに及ばぬ奇特とかや。
([JIUTAI] and their miraculous power is beyond expression!)
［地謡］また我が朝のそのはじめ。
([JIUTAI] And so, it was in the early days of our history,)
人皇十二代 景行天皇。
(the Twelfth of the Imperial Line, the Emperor Keikō,)
みこの尊の御名をば
(had a son known by the name)
日本武と申しゝが。
(Yamato-dake.)
九夷を退治の勅を受け。
(The wild barbarians! He received the order to subdue them.)
関の東も遥なる。
(The barrier check points far behind as yet further to the East.)
東の旅の道すがら
(The road of his journey to the Eastern provinces took him.)
伊勢や尾張の海面に立つ波までも
(Even at Ise and Owari the waves on the sea rise and return!)
帰る事よと羨み。
(With envy he wondered always,)
いつかわれも帰る波の
(when he too might find himself, with foam-drenched sleeves)
衣手にあらめやと。思ひつゞけて行くほどに。
(returning home, even as he continued on his way.)
［シテ］こゝやかしこの戦に
([SHITE] In the battles in one place and in the next)
［地謡］人馬巌窟に身を砕き
([JIUTAI] men and horses: their bodies crushed in their caverns,)
血は涿鹿の川となって
(their blood on the battlefields a river,)
紅波盾流し数度に及べる夷も
(their shields swept away on crimson waves again and again.)
兜を脱いで矛を伏せ
(Finally the barbarians removed their helmets,)
皆降参を申しけり。
(lay down their arms and were made to surrender.)
尊の御宇より御狩場を始め給へり。
(From the time of this Prince's reign, the royal sport of hunting was begun.)
頃は神無月。
(It was an incident that occurred,)
二十日余りの事なれば。
(on the twentieth day of the Tenth month:)
四方の紅葉も冬枯の
(Everywhere the autumn tints had faded,)
遠山にかゝる薄雪を
(and even on the distant winter withered mountains,)
眺めさせ給ひしに。
(the traces of the first snow fall could be seen.)
［シテ］夷四方を囲みつゝ。
([SHITE] The barbarians surrounding him on every side)
［地謡］枯野の草に火をかけ
([JIUTAI] Set fire to the grass of the withered fields, and as the blaze burned high)
余炎しきりに燃え来たり
(and as the blaze burned high with heavy lingering billows of smoke.)
かたき攻鼓を打ちかけて
(Began to beat their war drums in the signal to attack.)
火炎を放ちてかゝりければ。
(The Towering flames! as the attack blazed forward)
［シテ］尊は剣を抜いて。
([SHITE] The Prince drew his sword)
［地謡］尊は剣を抜いて。
([JIUTAI] The Prince drawing his sword,)
あたりを払ひ 忽ちに。
(wielded it about him.)
炎も立ち退けと
(At once, the flames drew back,)
四方の草を薙ぎ払へば。
(as it mowed down the grasses in all directions.)
剣の精霊嵐となつて
(The spirit of the sword became a storm)
炎も草も 吹き返されて。
(blasting back the raging flames and grasses too.)
天にかゞやき地に充ち／＼て。
(The blaze lit up the heavens, covered the earth!)
猛火は却つて敵を焼けば。
(A furnace of fierce flames turned back to devour the enemy forces.)
数万騎の夷どもは
(Thus, the countless barbarians,)
忽ちこゝにて失せてんげり。
(and cavalrymen were brought down.)
其後。四海治まりて
(So in later years the Empire was at peace:)
人家戸ざしを忘れしも。
(So much so that the people forgot to bar the doors of their houses.)
その草薙の故とかや。
(This is because of the 'Grass-cutter', it was said.)
只今汝が打つべき
(And now, this auspicious omened blade)
この瑞相の御剣も。
(that you must forge!)
いかでそれには劣るべき。
(Is there any reason it should be a lesser blade than that ?)
伝ふる家の宗近よ。
(Munechika, heir to a house of proud tradition,)
心安く思ひて下向し給へ。
(set your heart at rest and go home now.)
［ワキ］漢家本朝に於て剣の威徳。
([WAKI] What you have told me of the power of the swords in China and Japan)
時に取つての祝言申す。はかりのく候。
(has gladdened my heart at this important hour.)
さて／＼御身は如何なる人ぞ。
(Yet, I press you again to tell me who you are.)
［ワキ］よし誰なりとも頼むべし。
([SHITE] Who I may be is of no consequence, but you must pray!)
まづ／＼勅の御剣を。
(Before anything else adorn your forge mound)
打つべき壇を飾りつつ。
(where you will temper the Imperial blade.)
その時我を待ち給はゞ。
(And at that time, if you will but wait for me.)
［地謡］通力の身を変じ。
([JIUTAI] I will change into supernatural form.)
通力の身を変じて。
(Having changed into a supernatural form,)
必ずその時節に
(I will come without fail, at the appointed time,)
参り会ひて御力を。つけ申すべし。
(and join you, adding my strength to yours.)
待ち給へと。
(Then wait for me!)
夕雲の稲荷山。
(So saying, into the evening clouds of Mt. Inari)
行くへも知らず失せにけり
(without a sign of where he went, he vanished,)
行くへも知らず失せにけり。
(Without a sign of where he went, he vanished.)
斯様に候者は、稲荷大明神に
([KYŌGEN] I am the god of a subsidiary shrine)
仕へ申す末社の神にて候、
(and in the service of Inari-daimyōjin.)
只今是へ出ずること、余の義にあらず、
(I have come here before you now on a matter of no small importance.)
さても、人皇六十六代一條院、
(Now then, it seems that the Emperor Ichijo, sixty-sixth of the imperial line,)
この程、不思議の御告げましまして、
(has recently had a portentous dream oracle.)
三条の小鍛冶宗近に、
(According to it, the Sanjo swordsmith Munechika,)
御剣を打たせらるべきとの御事なり、
(must be ordered to forge a blade.)
すなわち道成卿、勅使となって、
(At that time Minister Michinari was the imperial envoy)
宣旨の趣き、仰られければ、
(who gave him the details of the imperial message.)
宗近、宣旨承り
(Munechika hearing the message, agreed to comply with the order,)
いか程大事に御剣を、打ち申すには、
(though to forge such an important blade,)
それがし一人にては計らいがたし、
(he said, was something he could not do by himself)
われに劣らぬ相槌無くては叶わじとて、
("As it will be impossible without an assistant of skill equal to my own,)
先ずはご辞退なされ候が綸言汗の如し、
(I should certainly refuse this order, but as this is a request from the Emperor himself,)
且つは家の面目と存じ、お受けを申され候、
(I know it would bring great shame to my house to decline and so I will accept it," he said.)
さりながら、この度の御剣を打ち申すには
(And so, as it would not be possible for him to forge the sword by himslef on this occasion,)
それがし一人にては計らいがたし、
(in order to do it he decided he must call on divine power,)
神力を頼もうずるとて、
(in other words, on Inari Daimyojin, his family's tutelary god.)
すなわち、稲荷大明神は氏神なり
(If indeed a deity could watch over his forge,)
ことさら、鍛治を守り給う御神なれば、
(he decided he must go at once and pray concerning the matter.)
只今参詣仕り候う所に
(As he did this so humbly, the god of the Inari shrine knew of it and,)
忝くも当社明神ご存じあって
(taking the form of a youth, appeared and met)
仮に童子の姿と現じ宗近に行き合い、
(with Munechika, and spoke to him.)
御言葉を交わされ候、
(Commonly, in our land there have been,)
総じて、我が朝において、
(from the Age of the Gods, two sacred swords.)
神代より伝うる霊剣、二つあり、
(The one called "Totsuka no Tsurugi", the Ten-span Sword)
十束の剣と申すは、須佐之男命、
(was used by Susanō-no-mikoto, when learning of the great serpent)
出雲の国、斐の川上に、大蛇のありしを、
(at the headwaters of the Hi River in the country of Izumo,)
従え給いしも、この剣の威徳なり、
(he destroyed it, due to the virtue of this sword.)
又、叢雲の剣と申すは、
(Then again, the sword called "Murakumo no Tsurugi" the Gathering Clouds Sword,)
そのとき大蛇の尾にありし剣なり、
(was the sword he found at that time in the tail of the great serpent.)
又、人皇十二代景行天皇、第二の皇子
(Then again, Yamatodake-no-mikoto the second son of Emperor Keikō,)
日本武尊命東夷を平らげ給いしも、
(the twelfth of the imperial line, subdued the people of the eastern lands,)
その剣の威徳なり、
(this also due to the virtue of that sword.)
それよりあらため、草薙の剣とは、これを申すなり、
(From that time, it was renamed and known as 'Kusanagi-no-Tsurugi" the Grass Cutting Sword.)
そのほか、漢の高祖、三尺の剣、
(In addition to these, there are the Han Emperor's Three Foot Sword,)
干将莫耶の剣、唐土我が朝において
(the Gan JIang and Mo Ye swords. He told him many stories)
剣の威徳、ことごとく御物語なされ、
(of the virtue of swords, both in China and in our own country.)
汝も、名を得たる鍛治なれば、いずれにおとらざる
("You, too, if you are a swordsmith of repute, will be able to forge a blade of equal merit.)
御剣を打ち申すなり、鉄を鍛うて待つべし、
(Prepare, temper the metal, and wait.")
その時明神来現あって、
(At that time, Myojin will appear and be your assistant)
相槌を打たせらるべきとの御事なれば、
(in forging the blade. This being the case,)
宗近も、喜びの眉をひらき、
(Munechika, his eyebrows relaxed in joy,)
只今、下向仕りて候、
(is even now coming this way to do these things.)
総じて何事も、祈請をかけ申せば、
(In this way then, whe prayers are offered)
諸願成就疑いなし、
(they shall be fulfilled, without a doubt.)
かまえてその分、心得候え、
(On this matter, rest assured,)
心得候え、
(rest assured.)
［ワキ］宗近勅に随つて
([WAKI] Now, I, Munichika, in compliance with the Imperial Will)
即ち壇にあがり
(have accordingly ascended the dais to ward off impurities.)
不浄を隔つる七重の注連
(It is adorned with the Seven-fold Sacred Rope,)
四方に本尊をかけ奉り
(and in the four corners sacred images placed in reverence.)
幣帛を捧げ　仰ぎ願はくは
(I raise up this Sacred wand and make my petition.)
人皇六十代
(Now, in the reign of the Sixty-sixth Emperor Ichijo,)
一条の院の御宇に
(I have been honored greatly in my craft,)
其職の誉を蒙る事
(through no effort of my own,)
これ私の力にあらず。
(rather, I have held in trust those skills.)
伊弉諾伊弉冉の尊
(When Izanagi and Izanami crossed over)
天の浮橋を踏みわたり
(the Floating Bridge of Heaven,)
豊芦原を探り給ひし
(and probed the Abundant Reed Plain)
御矛より始まれり。
(with the Sacred Spear was their beginning.)
その後南瞻僧伽陀国波斯
(Later, from holy Hashimida of Eastern India)
弥陀尊者より此方
(the descendants of Amakuni and Fujito)
天国ひつきの子孫に伝へて
(learned arts)
今に至れり。
(which I am now the master of.)
［ワキ］願はくは
([WAKI] Now, I pray!)
［地謡］願はくは
([JIUTAI] Now I petition: It is not for the glory of my name: Munechika,)
宗近私の功名にあらず。
(but at the imperial command of the Emperor,)
普天卒土の勅命によれり
(whose rule extends from heaven to earth, that I call on all divine beings,)
さあらば十方恒沙の諸神
(numberless as the sand of the Ganges,)
唯今の宗近に力を合はせてたび給へとて。
(to join your strength now with Munechika.)
幣帛を捧げつゝ
(I offer up this sacred wand.)
天に仰ぎ頭を地に付け。骨髄の丹誠聞き入れ
(I bow my head before heaven as I seek divine aid from my inmost being.)
納受。せしめ給へや。
(Hear and grant my prayer.)
［ワキ］謹上
([WAKI] With profound reverence:)
［地謡］再拝
([JIUTAI] My supplication!)
［地謡］いかにや宗近勅の剣。
([JIUTAI] Now, Munechika -- the Imperial Blade!)
いかにや宗近勅の剣
(Now, Munechika -- the Imperial Blade!)
打つべき時節は虚空に知れり。
(The appointed time for forging is known!)
頼めや頼め唯たのめ。
(Trust and have faith!  Only trust!)
［シテ］童男壇の。上にあがり。
([SHITE] A young boy ascends the forge mound!)
［地謡］童男壇の。上にあがつて
([JIUTAI] A young boy ascends the forge mound,)
宗近に三拝の膝を屈し。
(kneels and bows three times before Munechika.)
扨御剣の。鉄はと問へば
("Now then, the metal for the blade?" he says)
宗近も恐悦の心をさきとして
(and Munechika, his heart joyful, in reply)
鉄取り出し。
(brings for the metal.)
教の鎚をはつたと打てば。
(As he strikes the first blow with his mallet,)
［シテ］丁と打つ。
([SHITE] Clang! we strike!)
［地謡］丁
([JIUTAI] Clang!)
［シテ］丁と
([SHITE] Clang, again.)
［地謡］打ち重ねたる鎚の響。
([JIUTAI] The blows coming, one on another, the sound of their mallets)
天地に聞こえて おびたゝしや
(echoes throughout heaven and earth - How it resounds!)
［ワキ］かくて御剣を打ち奉り。
([WAKI] And so the Imperial Blade is forged:)
表に小鍛冶宗近と打つ。
(On the face of it I strike: "Munechika, Swordsmith"!)
［シテ］神体時の弟子なれば。
([SHITE] As your timely apprentice the god:)
小狐と裏にあざやかに。
("Little Fox", I skillfully strike on the reverse.)
打ち奉る御剣の。
([JIUTAI] Along the edge of the blade are beaten traces)
刃は雲を乱したれば。
(like wild clustering clouds.)
天の叢雲ともこれなれや。
("Clustering Clouds of Heaven", it will be!)
天下第一の。
([SHITE] First under Heaven:)
([JIUTAI] First under Heaven:)
二つの銘の御剣にて。
(The sword with two inscriptions!)
四海を治め給へば。
(It will rule the land to the four seas,)
五穀成就も此時なれや。
(celebrate the abundance of the five staple crops.)
即ち汝が氏の神。
("I, before you, as the deity of your clan:)
稲荷の神体小狐丸を。
(the manifestation of Inari: the Little Fox,)
勅使に捧げ申し。
(come to aid you in fulfilling your task.)
これまでなりと言ひ捨てゝ。
(Now, I am done!" So saying, takes his leave.)
又群雲に飛び乗り。
(Once more he leaps upon the mass of clouds,)
又群雲に飛びのりて
(Again, more he leaps upon the mass of clouds,)
東山稲荷の峯にぞ帰りける。
(and return to Higashiyama, the eastern mountains, the peak of Mt. Inari!)